阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@ Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
大家好 我是凯莉·安 欢迎来到计算机科学速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne, and welcome to Crash Course Computer Science!
前6集 我们深入研究了软件 从早期的编程工作
Over the past six episodes, we delved into software, from early programming efforts to
到现代软件工程的实践
modern software engineering practices.
50年里 软件的复杂度从手打在纸带上的机器码
Within about 50 years, software grew in complexity from machine code punched by hand
到面向对象的编程语言
onto paper tape, to object oriented programming languages,
并在集成开发环境编译
compiled in integrated development environments.
但是这个复杂度的增加离不开
But this growth in sophistication would not have been possible
硬件的提高
without improvements in hardware.
要理解计算机硬件的功率和复杂度的爆炸增长
To appreciate computing hardware's explosive growth in power and sophistication,
要回到电子计算机的诞生时期
we need to go back to the birth of electronic computing.
从大约1940年代到1960年代中期 每个电脑
From roughly the 1940's through the mid-1960s, every computer was built
都是由单独的部分组成 叫做分立元件 全部由线连接
from individual parts, called discrete components, which were all wired together.
比如 ENIAC计算机由超过17,000真空管70,000电阻器
For example, the ENIAC, consisted of more than 17,000 vacuum tubes, 70,000 resistors,
10,000电容器和7,000二极管组成
10,000 capacitors, and 7,000 diodes,
这些需要5百万手工焊接
all of which required 5 million hand-soldered connections.
增加元件提高性能意味着更多连接和线路
Adding more components to increase performance meant more connections, more wires,
更加复杂  被戏称为数字暴政
and just more complexity, what was dubbed the Tyranny of Numbers.
1950年代中期 晶体管商业化成功
By the mid 1950s, transistors were becoming commercially available
并装备进计算机
and being incorporated into computers.
他们比真空管更小更快更可靠
These were much smaller, faster and more reliable than vacuum tubes,
但是每个晶体管仍是一个分立元件
but each transistor was still one discrete component.
1959年 IBM把709计算机升级
In 1959, IBM upgraded their vacuum-tube-based “709” computers to transistors
将分立真空管替换为分立晶体管
by replacing all the discrete vacuum tubes with discrete transistors.
新的计算机 IBM 7090是原来的6倍快 花费一半
The new machine, the IBM 7090, was six times faster and half the cost.
这些晶体管计算机是电子计算机的第二代的标志
These transistorized computers marked the second generation of electronic computing.
但是 尽管更快更小 分立晶体管
However, although faster and smaller, discrete transistors didn't
没有解决数字暴政
solve the Tyranny of Numbers.
设计起来更困难 更不用说实际制造计算机
It was getting unwieldy to design, let alone physically manufacture computers
用到上千的独立组件
with hundreds of thousands of individual components.
到了1960年代 晶体管计算机到达了极限
By the the 1960s, this was reaching a breaking point.
计算机内部常常是大量缠绕的电线
The insides of computers were often just huge tangles of wires.
看看1965年的 PDP-8内部长什么样吧
Just look at what the inside of a PDP-8 from 1965 looked like!
答案是上升到新一层的抽象
The answer was to bump up a new level of abstraction,
把内部复杂的结构包装起来
and package up underlying complexity!
1958年有了突破 德州仪器的杰克·基尔比
The breakthrough came in 1958, when Jack Kilby, working at Texas Instruments,
展示了这样一个电子部件
demonstrated such an electronic part,
“这里所有的电子电路的部件都完全成为一体”
“wherein all the components of the electronic circuit are completely integrated.“
简单来说 不是用分离元件搭建计算机的部件
Put simply: instead of building computer parts out of many discrete components
把它们连起来 把很多元件放在一起
and wiring them all together, you put many components together,
放在一个新的单个元件
inside of a new, single component.
它们叫做集成电路 简称IC
These are called Integrated Circuits, or ICs.
同样在1959年几个月后 仙童半导体公司由罗伯特·诺伊斯
A few months later in 1959, Fairchild Semiconductor, lead by Robert Noyce,
使IC能实用
made ICs practical.
基尔比用锗这一稀有且不稳定的元素造IC
Kilby built his ICs out of germanium, a rare and unstable material.
但是 仙童公司使用大储量的硅
But, Fairchild used the abundant silicon,
占地壳的四分之一
which makes up about a quarter of the earth's crust!
而且更加稳定 从而更加可靠
It's also more stable, therefore more reliable.
因此诺伊斯被认为是IC之父
For this reason, Noyce is widely regarded as the father of modern ICs,
引领了电子时代 以及硅谷
ushering in the electronics era... and also Silicon Valley,
仙童公司就建于此 随后许多其他半导体公司
where Fairchild was based and where many other semiconductor companies
迅速发展起来
would soon pop up.
过去 一个IC可能只含有一个简单电路和几个晶体管
In the early days, an IC might only contain a simple circuit with just a few transistors,
例如这个西屋公司的
like this early Westinghouse example.
即使这个IC也能使简单电路 如第3集的逻辑门
But even this allowed simple circuits, like the logic gates from Episode 3,
包装到一个单独部件中
to be packaged up into a single component.
IC有点像 计算机工程师用来建造房屋的乐高
ICs are sort of like lego for computer engineers “building blocks” that can be arranged
可以被排列成无限可能的设计
into an infinite array of possible designs.
但是 它们必要时仍然要用线连接
However, they still have to be wired together at some point to create even bigger
形成更复杂的电路 像是电脑
and more complex circuits, like a whole computer.
为此 工程师有了另一个创新：印刷电路板 简称PCB
For this, engineers had another innovation: printed circuit boards, or PCBs.
不再焊接和捆绑不计其数的电线
Instead of soldering and bundling up bazillions of wires,
PCB可以大量生产
PCBs, which could be mass manufactured,
把所有金属线刻上来连接不同部件
have all the metal wires etched right into them to connect components together.
同时用到PCB和IC
By using PCBs and ICs together, one could achieve exactly the same
可以实现分立元件相同功能的电路
functional circuit as that made from discrete components,
但是远远更少的分立元件和缠绕的线
but with far fewer individual components and tangled wires.
另外 它更便宜 更可靠
Plus, it's smaller, cheaper and more reliable.
三赢
Triple win!
许多早期IC用小的分立元件制作
Many early ICs were manufactured using teeny tiny discrete components
包装形成一个单独的单元 像是这个IBM1964年的
packaged up as a single unit, like this IBM example from 1964.
但是 即使使用非常非常小的元件
However, even when using really really itty-bitty components,
把超过5个晶体管装到一个IC上也是困难的
it was hard to get much more than around five transistors onto a single IC.
为了完成更复杂的设计
To achieve more complex designs, a radically different fabrication process
需要完全不同的制作方法 光刻法
was needed that changed everything: Photolithography!
简单来说 这个方法用光线把复杂的图案转移到一块材料上
In short, it's a way to use light to transfer complex patterns to a material,
像是半导体
like a semiconductor.
只有基本的几个操作
It only has a few basic operations, but these can be used
却可以创造非常复杂的电路
to create incredibly complex circuits.
让我们过一遍简单但广泛的例子 制作一个电路
Let's walk through a simple, although extensive example, to make one of these!
从一片硅开始 像是一片薄饼干 叫做晶片
We start with a slice of silicon, which, like a thin cookie, is called a wafer.
美味
Delicious!
在第2集简单说过 硅的特殊在于它是半导体
Silicon, as we discussed briefly in episode 2, is special because it's a semiconductor,
半导体有时会传导电流 有时不会
that is, a material that can sometimes conduct electricity and other times does not.
我们能控制什么位置什么时候通断
We can control where and when this happens,
硅成了完美的制造晶体管的原料
making Silicon the perfect raw material for making transistors.
我们把晶片作为基底承接复杂金属电路
We can also use a wafer as a base to lay down complex metal circuits,
所以一切是集合的 完美适合制作 集成电路
so everything is integrated, perfect for... integrated circuits!
下一步是加一层薄的氧化层在硅上面
The next step is to add a thin oxide layer on top of the silicon,
作为保护涂层
which acts as a protective coating.
然后加上一种特殊的化学物质叫做光致抗蚀剂
Then, we apply a special chemical called a photoresist.
当曝露在光下 这个化学物质变得可溶
When exposed to light, the chemical changes, and becomes soluble,
可被一种特殊化学物质洗掉
so it can be washed away with a different special chemical.
光致抗蚀剂本身没用
Photoresists aren't very useful by themselves,
但是跟光掩膜一起就很有用
but are super powerful when used in conjunction with a photomask.
它像是一片照片的胶片 不过不是
This is just like a piece of photographic film, but instead of a photo of a hamster
一个仓鼠吃着玉米煎饼的照片 而是需要转移到晶体上的图案
eating a tiny burrito, it contains a pattern to be transferred onto the wafer.
把光掩膜放在晶片上 打开大功率灯
We do this by putting a photomask over the wafer, and turning on a powerful light.
膜挡住了灯光 光致抗溶剂不变
Where the mask blocks the light, the photoresist is unchanged.
光线照射的光致抗蚀剂会产生化学变化
But where the light does hit the photoresist it changes chemically
我们只能洗去暴露在光下的光之抗蚀剂
which lets us wash away only the photoresist that was exposed to light,
有选择地暴露氧化层
selectively revealing areas of our oxide layer.
现在使用另一种特殊化学物质 通常是酸
Now, by using another special chemical, often an acid,
可以去除暴露的氧化层
we can remove any exposed oxide,
然后蚀刻小洞一直到硅层
and etch a little hole the entire way down to the raw silicon.
注意光致抗蚀剂下面的氧化层是被保护的
Note that the oxide layer under the photoresist is protected.
我们用另一种特殊化学物质
To clean up, we use yet another special chemical
洗去残留的光之抗蚀剂
that washes away any remaining photoresist.
没错 光刻法用到了许多特殊化学品
Yep, there are a lot of special chemicals in photolithography,
每一个都有专门的用途
each with a very specific function!
现在我们再看看硅片 我们想设置只有暴露的部分
So now we can see the silicon again, we want to modify only the exposed areas
能传导电流
to better conduct electricity.
为了实现 需要采用一步化学方法改变它 叫做显影
To do that, we need to change it chemically through a process called: doping.
我不在开玩笑
I'm not even going to make a joke.
我们继续
Let's move on.
通常在高温气体下进行
Most often this is done with a high temperature gas,
类似磷 渗透到硅片的暴露区域
something like Phosphorus, which penetrates into the exposed area of silicon.
从而改变电学性质性质
This alters its electrical properties.
我们不涉及半导体的物理和化学原理
We're not going to wade into the physics and chemistry of semiconductors,
如果你感兴趣 描述栏里有
but if you're interested, there's a link in the description
Veritasium频道我们朋友德里克·穆勒的视频链接
to an excellent video by our friend Derek Muller from Veritasium.
但是我们还需要几轮光刻才能造成一个晶体管
But, we still need a few more rounds of photolithography to build a transistor.
过程再次开始 首先加上氧化层
The process essentially starts again, first by building up a fresh oxide layer
再覆盖上光致抗溶剂
which we coat in photoresist.
现在我们用不同图案的光掩膜
Now, we use a photomask with a new and different pattern,
可以在显影区域上方开一个小窗户
allowing us to open a small window above the doped area.
再一次 洗去残留的光致抗蚀剂
Once again, we wash away remaining photoresist.
现在我们显影 但用不同的气体
Now we dope, and avoid telling a hilarious joke, again, but with a different gas
把一部分硅转化成不同的形式
that converts part of the silicon into yet a different form.
光刻法里时间对控制很重要
Timing is super important in photolithography in order to control things
像是显影的扩散和刻蚀的深度
like doping diffusion and etch depth.
这里 我们只想在其他区域里显影一小块区域
In this case, we only want to dope a little region nested inside the other.
现在有了构建晶体管的所有部件了
Now we have all the pieces we need to create our transistor!
最后一步是在氧化层里打通道
The final step is to make channels in the oxide layer
这样就可以在晶体管不同部分排布小导线了
so that we can run little metal wires to different parts of our transistor.
再次 覆盖光致抗蚀剂 用光掩膜 刻蚀更小的通道
Once more, we apply a photoresist, and use a new photomask to etch little channels.
现在 用一个新的过程 叫金属化
Now, we use a new process, called metalization,
我们覆盖一层薄的金属 像是铝或铜
that allows us to deposit a thin layer of metal, like aluminium or copper.
但是我们不想金属覆盖住所有
But we don't want to cover everything in metal.
而是刻出特定的电路
We want to etch a very specific circuit design.
所以 跟前面相似 我们覆盖光致抗蚀剂
So, very similar to before, we apply a photoresist, use a photomask,
溶解暴露的抗蚀剂 去除暴露的金属
dissolve the exposed resist, and use a chemical to remove any exposed metal.
咻 我们的晶体管终于完成了
Whew! Our transistor is finally complete!
它有三个小导线连接连接硅片的不同部分
It has three little wires that connect to three different parts of the silicon,
每个显影特定的线路
each doped a particular way to create,
形成了这里的双极型晶体管
in this example, what's called a bipolar junction transistor.
这是1962年真实的图案 它永久改变了我们的世界
Here's the actual patent from 1962, an invention that changed our world forever!
用相同的步骤 光刻法可以创造其他有用的电子元件
Using similar steps, photolithography can create other useful electronic elements,
像是电阻器和电容器 都在一块硅片上
like resistors and capacitors, all on a single piece of silicon
（加上连接成电路的导线）
(plus all the wires needed to hook them up into circuits).
再见分立元件
Goodbye discrete components!
这个例子里我们做了一个晶体管 实际上
In our example, we made one transistor, but in the real world,
光掩膜瞬间设置百万的细节
photomasks lay down millions of little details all at once.
这是IC从上面看的样子
Here is what an IC might look like from above,
导线上下彼此交叉
with wires crisscrossing above and below each other,
连接所有独立的单元形成复杂的电路
interconnecting all the individual elements together into complex circuits.
虽然我们可以制造整个基底的光掩膜
Although we could create a photomask for an entire wafer,
不过我们利用光的聚焦性质
we can take advantage of the fact that light can be focused
投影到我们想要的大小
and projected to any size we want.
与电影胶片投影到整个荧幕相同
In the same way that a film can be projected to fill an entire movie screen,
我们可以把光掩膜聚焦到一块很小的硅上
we can focus a photomask onto a very small patch of silicon,
创造非常精密的细节
creating incredibly fine details.
一个硅晶片通常可以制作几十个IC
A single silicon wafer is generally used to create dozens of ICs.
当一整个晶片填满了 切开
Then, once you've got a whole wafer full, you cut them up and package them
并包装成微型芯片 就是那种你在电子产品中常见的黑色小矩形
into microchips, those little black rectangles you see in electronics all the time.
记住：那些芯片的核心
Just remember: at the heart of each of those chips
都是这些小的硅片
is one of these small pieces of silicon.
随着光刻技术的进步 晶体管的尺寸缩小了
As photolithography techniques improved, the size of transistors shrunk,
密度更大
allowing for greater densities.
1960年代初期一个IC很少超过5个晶体管
At the start of the 1960s, an IC rarely contained more than 5 transistors,
不可能放得下
they just couldn't possibly fit.
但是到了1960年代中期
But, by the mid 1960s,
市面上开始有了超过100个晶体管的IC
we were starting to see ICs with over 100 transistors on the market.
1965年 戈登·摩尔看到了趋势：大约每两年
In 1965, Gordon Moore could see the trend: that approximately every two years,
得益于材料和制造技术的进步
thanks to advances in materials and manufacturing,
可以在同样的空间内装两倍的晶体管
you could fit twice the number of transistors into the same amount of space.
这叫摩尔定律
This is called Moore's Law.
但是这个定律有点错误
The term is a bit of a misnomer though.
他并不是真正的定律 更像是趋势
It's not really a law at all, more of a trend.
但很准确
But it's a good one.
IC价格也巨幅下降 从平均1962年平均50刀到1968年2刀
IC prices also fell dramatically, from an average of $50 in 1962 to around $2 in 1968.
今天 你可以只花几分钱买到IC
Today, you can buy ICs for cents.
更小的晶体管和更高的密度还有别的优点
Smaller transistors and higher densities had other benefits too.
更小的晶体管需要更少的电量驱动
The smaller the transistor, the less charge you have to move around,
可以更快的切换状态并消耗更少能量
allowing it to switch states faster and consume less power.
另外 更紧凑的电路意味着更少的信号延迟从而加快时钟频率
Plus, more compact circuits meant less delay in signals resulting in faster clock speeds.
1968年 罗伯特·诺伊斯和戈登·摩尔合作成立了一个新的公司
In 1968, Robert Noyce and Gordon Moore teamed up and founded a new company,
把集成和电子两个词合并成Intel 今天最大的芯片制造商
combining the words Integrated and Electronics...Intel... the largest chip maker today.
第7和8集的Intel 4004 CPU是一个巨大的里程碑
The Intel 4004 CPU, from Episodes 7 and 8, was a major milestone.
发行于1971年 是第一个上市的IC处理器
Released in 1971, it was the first processor that shipped as an IC,
它被叫做微型处理器 因为它真的很小
what's called a microprocessor, because it was so beautifully small!
它含有2,300个晶体管
It contained 2,300 transistors.
人们惊叹于集成的水平高到把一整个CPU放进一个芯片
People marveled at the level of integration, an entire CPU in one chip,
而20年前会占满整个屋子
which just two decades earlier would have filled an entire room
当时用分立元件
using discrete components.
集成电路尤其是微处理器的时代
This era of integrated circuits, especially microprocessors,
引领了第三代计算
ushered in the third generation of computing.
而Intel 4004就是开始
And the Intel 4004 was just the start.
CPU的晶体管数量爆炸增长
CPU transistor count exploded!
到了1980年 CPU有3万晶体管
By 1980, CPUs contained 30 thousand transistors.
1990年 突破了1百万
By 1990, CPUs breached the 1 million transistor count.
2000年 3千万
By 2000, 30 million transistors,
2010年 10亿 哦买噶
and by 2010, ONE BILLION TRANSISTORS IN ONE IC. OMG!
为了达到这个密度 光刻法最细可能分辨率
To achieve this density, the finest resolution possible with photolithography
从1万纳米
has improved from roughly 10 thousand nanometers,
即十分之一发丝厚度 提升到
that's about 1/10th the thickness of a human hair,
今天14纳米
to around 14 nanometers today.
比红细胞还小400倍
That's over 400 times smaller than a red blood cell!
当然 CPU不是唯一受益的元件
And of course, CPU's weren't the only components to benefit.
绝大多数电子产品 以指数进步
Most electronics advanced essentially exponentially:
RAM 显卡 固态硬盘 相机传感器 等等
RAM, graphics cards, solid state hard drives, camera sensors, you name it.
今天的处理器 像是iPhone 7里的A10 CPU
Today's processors, like the A10 CPU inside Of an iPhone 7,
在1cm×1cm的大小的IC里竟然含有33亿晶体管
contains a mind melting 3.3 BILLION transistors in an IC roughly 1cm by 1cm.
比一张邮票还小
That's smaller than a postage stamp!
现代工程师并不是手工设计
And modern engineers aren't laying out these designs by hand,
一次放一个 人工不可能
one transistor at a time - it's not humanly possible.
1970年代超大尺寸集成软件 简称VLSI软件
Starting in the 1970's, very-large-scale integration, or VLSI software,
被用于自动生产芯片设计
has been used to automatically generate chip designs instead.
使用逻辑综合技术布置整个的高级部件
Using techniques like logic synthesis, where whole, high-level components
像是缓存
can be laid down, like a memory cache,
这个软件最高效地产生电路
the software generates the circuit in the most efficient way possible.
很多人认为这是计算机第四代的开始
Many consider this to be the start of fourth generation computers.
不幸的是 专家预计摩尔定律将在几十年内结束
Unfortunately, experts have been predicting the end of Moore's Law for decades,
我们可能很接近了
and we might finally be getting close to it.
进一步缩小有两个大问题
There are two significant issues holding us back from further miniaturization.
首先 我们达到了光掩膜上的图案分辨率的极限
First, we're bumping into limits on how fine we can make features on a photomask
光刻发用的光的波长导致了晶片
and it's resultant wafer due to the wavelengths of light used in photolithography.
为了应对 科学家开发光源
In response, scientists have been developing light sources
的波长越来越短 从而投影更小的图案
with smaller and smaller wavelengths that can project smaller and smaller features.
第二个问题是晶体管越来越小
The second issue is that when transistors get really really small,
这样电极可能只被几十个原子分隔
where electrodes might be separated by only a few dozen atoms,
电子可以越过这个间隔 这一现象叫做量子隧穿
electrons can jump the gap, a phenomenon called quantum tunneling.
如果晶体管泄露电流 就不是合格的开关
If transistors leak current, they don't make very good switches.
尽管如此 科学家和工程师努力
Nonetheless, scientists and engineers are hard at work
寻找解决方法
figuring out ways around these problems.
1nm的晶体管已经在实验室展示出来
Transistors as small as 1 nanometer have been demonstrated in research labs.
是否将来能商业化仍是个谜
Whether this will ever be commercially feasible remains MASKED in mystery.
可能将来会解决
But maybe we'll be able to RESOLVE it in the future.
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@ Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
我很想知道
I'm dying to know.
下周见
See you next week.